（カイト）ルーク！
Rook!
[TEL]（バロン）カイト君が？！
（ソウジ）はい　学園長。
Kaito is?!
Yes, Principal.
[TEL]容体は？
意識が　まだ戻りません。
How is he?
He's still unconscious.
ただ　医師の話では
[TEL]そうですか。
大事に至る外傷はなく→
I see.
But the doctors say he has no significant wounds,
精密検査の結果にも　異常は…。
and detailed examinations also showed nothing.
間もなく　意識も
戻るだろうとのことです。
He could regain consciousness any moment.
（ノノハ）よかった…　カイト。
I'm glad, Kaito...
kimi no nounai he shinnyuu nemutteiru sukima ni
I infiltrate your brain while you're sleeping.
Baby, open the gate!
fukuzatsu sugi sekyuriti kakusareru to abakitaku naru
The security's too tough, but I want to expose what's hidden.
barabara ni chirabatteiru pasuwado wo hiroi atsume
I gather the pieces of the shattered password.
kakushin ni sematte iku sono shoutai wo misete
I get close to the core. Show me who you really are!
kantan ni kuria dekinai saki nante motto yomenai
I can't clear it easily. I can't even see what lies ahead.
kaidoku fukanou sumairu kikenna pazuru
Your indecipherable smile is a hazardous puzzle.
rokku sareta doa aru nara zutto tataite miru beki kazana hiraku wa
When you see a locked door, you should just hit it until a crack opens.
eien ni hodokenai nazo nanka wa nai
There's no mystery that lasts forever!
makiokosu, it's a supernova
I made it, it's a supernova!
tobikiri shigekitekina hirameki wo agemashou
Let's flash so bright it'd hurt!
Misskey-Misskey La-Tu-Ma
yume no naka it's a supernova
In my dreams, it's a supernova!
watashi wa sou brain diver
Yeah, I'm the brain diver!
kimi ga sagashi motometeru kotae ni nareru made
Until I can find the answer you're looking for...
Brain diver!
The Right to Friendship
（ギャモン）
…ったく　バカだバカだとは思って
たけどよ　いくら親友だからって→
I knew he was a total moron, but still...
Even if it's his old friend, he tagged along with a leader of the POG just like that?
ＰＯＧの　しかも幹部なんかに
ホイホイ　ついていくか？　普通。
Kaito didn't know.
（アナ）カイトは知らなかった。
だから　バカだっつってんだよ。
That's why I said he's a total moron.
アナが思うに　ギャモンは　カイトのことが
ホントに好きなんだね。
I think... you really like Kaito, Gammon.
はぁ？！　何で　俺が？
Huh?! Me?!
（キュービック）僕も　そう思う。
なんだよ！　お前まで。
I agree.
What, you too?!
（キュービック）カイトはバカだ。　僕を置いて
イギリスなんか行くからだよ。
Kaito is a moron. He left for England without me.
あんなやつと一緒に！
おっ　おい！
With a guy like that!
H-Hey!
キューちゃん！
（ドアの開閉する音）
Cubie!
…ったく　何が「愚者のパズル」だ。
Who cares about the Fools' Puzzle?!
何が　ファイ・ブレインの子供たちだ！
マジ　バカみてえな話ばっかだぜ。
Who cares about all that Phi Brain crap?!
It's so stupid I can't even believe it.
So fucking stupid!
くっだらねえ！
（ごみ箱を蹴る音）
[TEL]（バロン）では　やはり彼が…。
So, it was him?
Yes, it was Chief Crossfield.
はい　クロスフィールド管理官の仕業です。
いかがいたしましょう？
What should I do?
[TEL]（バロン）相手は
ＰＯＧの全権を委ねられた→
Your opponent has all the power of the POG behind him.
[TEL]いわば　伯爵の懐刀です。
軽はずみな行動は控えてください。
You could call him the Count's greatest weapon.
Don't do anything rash.
分かりました。
[TEL]（バロン）では…。
I understand.
Very well.
なんて言ってはみたものの　仲間が
やられっぱなしってのはね…。
But even if you say that, no one would be okay with their friend being knocked out.
何気に性に合わなかったりして。
I must show him.
思い知らせてやんなきゃね。
I'll show him who's worthy of being at Kaito's side.
カイトと一緒にいるのに
ふさわしいのは　誰なのかを。
ルーク・盤城・クロスフィールドに。
Rook Banjo Crossfield...
ん？！　あれ？！
どこだろう？　ここ。
Huh? Where am I?
これって…。
That's...
モールス信号だ！
Morse code!
（キュービック）「…まで来い！　エジソンへ」。
...come, Edison!
They're calling me!
僕を呼んでる！
ちょうど　よかった。
Perfect. I've been thinking of how to avenge Kaito anyway.
どこへ行けば　カイトの敵が討てるか
考えてたとこだったんだ。
（ビショップ）これより先　大門カイトが
歩むは　死と隣り合わせの道。
Daimon Kaito is walking a path sided with death.
ともに進めば　君には必ずや
苦難の道が待ち受ける。
If you accompany him, you will surely face great suffering as well.
それでも　行くと言うなら→
If you are still willing to do so,
challenge the puzzle made by Rook Banjo Crossfield,
このルーク・盤城・クロスフィールドが作りし
パズルに挑み　覚悟を示せ。
and prove your determination.
死を恐れぬ　愚か者の証しを…。
The proof of the fool who doesn't fear death.
I have sent the message to Cubic Galois as you ordered.
（ビショップ）以上　ご命令どおり
キュービック・Ｇにメッセージを伝えました。
（ルーク）ご苦労。
Well done.
All is going according to your plan.
（ビショップ）
計画は　ルーク様の思惑どおりに
滞りなく進んでおりますが→
しかし　なぜ…。
But why...
They are just stones weighing Kaito down.
（ルーク）彼らは　カイトに
まとわりついたカビだ。
こそげ落とせば　きっとカイトも
本気を出してくれる…。
If we clear them away, I'm sure Kaito will get serious as well.
だよね。
（お湯をかける音）
Right?
彼の話をするとき　カイトは
とても遠く　いとしい目をする。
When talking about him, Kaito looked so nostalgic, so distant...
私には　決して
見せてくれたことのない目。
A kind of look that he would never show me.
私ね　たまに思うことがあったの。
Sometimes I think about it, you know...
カイトの時計は　ひょっとしたら
彼と過ごした時間の中で→
Maybe Kaito is stuck in the time he spent with him...
止まってしまったんじゃないか…
って。
And when I saw his face shining with happiness
√学園で　彼と再会したカイトの
はじけそうな笑顔を見たとき→
after they reunited at the Root Academy, I knew I was right.
ああ　やっぱり　そうなんだって…。
ねえ　アナ　私　分かんない。
そんなカイトを　どうして　ルーク君は…。
But I don't get it, Ana.
Even though Kaito was like that, why did Rook do this to him?
だって　カイトは　絶対に悪いやつを→
Kaito would never become friends with a bad person!
親友だなんて
思ったりしないもん！
カイトの友達ってことは　絶対に
いい子に決まってるもん。
Kaito only befriends good people.
うん。　アナも　そう思う。
だったら　どうして？！
Yeah, I think so too.
But then why?
アナも　そう思う。
だから　言ってんだろ。
I think so too...
That's why I said he's a moron.
カイトは　バカだって。
バカの友達は　結局　バカなんだよ。
A moron's friends are morons as well.
（キュービック）
ん。　廃棄された軍の基地か…。
An abandoned military base?
お望みどおり　来てあげたよ！
ＰＯＧ！
I came as you wanted, POG!
誰も居ないの？！　僕みたいな天才を
呼び出しておいて　待たせる気？！
No one's here?
You dare call a genius like me here and make me wait?
それとも　おじけづいちゃった？
Or did you get scared and run?
（フンガ）行く手に待つのは　死である
と　お伝えしたにもかかわらず→
Even though we told you that only death awaits you on this path,
よく逃げ出さずに
いらっしゃいましたね。
you have still come.
Normally I would praise you,
本来なら　褒めて差し上げたい
ところですが→
この場合　あなたに捧げるに
ふさわしい言葉は　「愚か者」です。
but this time, the only word I could find that suits you is "fool".
誰？　おじさん。　僕は　ルークと
勝負しに来てやったんだ。
Who are you?
I came here to challenge Rook.
カイトに　ひどい事したのは
あいつだろう？　呼んできてよ。
He did that to Kaito, didn't he? Call him here.
（フンガ）ご冗談を。
あなたごときのために→
You must be jesting. Why would Sir Rook bother with you?
ルーク様が　わざわざ
お越しくださるはずなど。
僕は　カイトの敵をとりに来たんだ。
いいから早く　やつを呼べよ！
I came here to take the head of Kaito's enemy! Call him already!
Silence!
黙れ！
うっ。
（フンガ）ルーク様に　盾つこうなどとは
まさに愚か者の極致。
The fact that you oppose Sir Rook is proof of your foolishness in itself.
（キュービック）僕は　カイトの友達だからね。
敵をとるのは　当然だよ。
Kaito is my friend. It's only natural I should avenge him.
Your friend? You claim you are worthy of being Daimon Kaito's friend?
友達？！　はて　あなたに大門カイトの
友達を名乗る資格がおありだと？
アハッ。
I invited you here today because there is something I need to tell you.
本日　お呼びしたのは
お伝えしたい事があったからです。
帰って　他のお仲間にも
伝えていただけますか？
Would you tell your other friends as well on your way home?
皆さんは大門カイトの成長を邪魔する
足手まといな存在ですので→
All of you are obstacles in the way of Daimon Kaito's growth.
とっとと　彼の周りから
消えてください。
Get away from him already.
You're fascinating, mister. I'm a genius.
面白いことを言うね　おじさん。
僕は天才だよ。
カイトの友達にふさわしいに
決まってるじゃない。
Of course I'm worthy of being his friend.
フッ。　しかたありませんね。
Seems I have no choice.
では　それを
証明していただきましょう。
You have the opportunity to prove it.
これ　何？
What's this?
A puzzle that Sir Rook has been so kind as to prepare for you.
（フンガ）今回ルーク様が　あなたのために
ご用意されたパズルです。
それでは　ルールを説明しましょう。
Let me explain the rules.
１～５まで　モニターがオンになる順に
パズルを解いてください。
Solve the puzzles so that monitors one to five will turn on in that order.
それぞれのカウンターが
ゼロになる前に→
That is, before their counters reach zero.
パズルの周囲を取り囲む数式の答えが
すべて１０になるように打ち込む。
You must fill in the numbers so that each line's result will be 10.
１つの式の中に　同じ数字を
入れてはいけません。
In each line, you can only use each number once.
Some numbers have parts lit. Are those hints?
（キュービック）
数字が　一部しか表示されてない。
（キュービック）これが　ヒントってこと？
（フンガ）そのとおりです。
Exactly.
（キュービック）最初は　これ？
This one first.
（フンガ）よっぽど　死に急ぎたい
ご様子ですね。
It seems you're in a hurry to die.
フン。
では　始めましょうか。
Then let it begin.
破壊へと向かう愚か者の行進を…。
The way of the fool to destruction.
If I have to make every side ten, then here can only be "2 x 5" or "5 x 2".
心の声
（キュービック）
１辺を１０にするということは→
心の声
この辺は　２×５か
５×２しかありえない。
Suppose I put 5 here, then it can be only something less than 2.
心の声
仮に　ここへ　５が入ると
ここは　２以外は入らない。
心の声
１を入れてしまうと
ラストは　５になり→
But if I put 1 here, then the last one would be 5 as well,
心の声
同じ辺に同じ数字が
２つ入って　不成立。
meaning two of the same number in a row, which is against the rules.
心の声
よって　この辺に入る
数字は　２と５ということになる。
Therefore, it can only be 2 here, and 5 here.
単純なトライ＆エラーの
心の声
繰り返しじゃないか。
This is just a simple repetition of trial and error.
楽勝だね。
心の声
It's easy.
うっ　うん。
カイト？
Kaito?
（ノノハ・アナ）はぁ。
ノノハ　ギャモン　アナ。　なんで？
Nonoha... Gammon... Ana... Why...?
カイト！　カイト　カイト　カイト～！
Kaito! Kaito!
痛い　痛い！　痛いって　ノノハ！
ごめん。
うふっ。
Ouch! That hurts, Nonoha!
Sorry!
よかった。
I'm so glad...
ルーク。　うっ。
Rook!
あっ？！　カイト！
てぇ！　どこ行く？
Kaito!
Where are you going?
どけ　ギャモン
確かめなきゃなんねえ事が　俺…。
Out of my way, Gammon.
I have to make sure of something.
Wake up already!
目を覚ませ！　お前
殺されそうになったんだぞ！
You almost got killed!
うるせえ！
いいかげんにしろ！
Shut up!
Cut it out already!
I'm in a terribly bad mood today.
俺は　今　猛烈に
虫の居所が悪いんだ。
バカたれが…。
Dumbass.
アハッ。
（キュービック）
こんなパズル　解けないわけないよ。
A puzzle like this is no challenge for me!
だって　僕は　天才だからね。
I'm a genius! A lot better than that Rook who made this!
これを作ったルークなんかより
ずっと…。
（警告音）
しまった！
Damn!
（フンガ）おや？
口ほどにもありませんね。
Oh? What did you say?
違うよ！　間違えたんじゃない！
手が滑ったんだ。
No! It's not a mistake! My hand just slipped!
Worry not. Death will approach slowly.
（フンガ）ご安心ください。
死は　ゆっくりと近づいてきます。
（フンガ）
最後のパズルを解き損じたとき→
However, when you fail to solve the last puzzle,
砲弾は　確実に
この格納庫を直撃します。
the shell will hit this building.
What's the problem now? I don't think you have the time to be trembling.
（フンガ）何を今さら…。
震えている場合じゃありませんよ。
（フンガ）ナンバー２のコンピューターは
とっくに　カウントダウンを始めてます。
The second computer has already begun counting down.
I forgot to mention something important.
（フンガ）そうそう。
大事なことを言い忘れていました。
パズルが解けなくても　あなたが
生き延びる方法があるという事を。
There is a way for you to stay alive without solving the puzzle.
簡単なことですよ。
It is simple. Simply escape.
このパズルから
逃げ出してしまえばいい。
That must have been hard, Kaito.
そっか。　大変だったんだね　カイト。
Do you want to be alone?
１人に　なりたい？
行こう　ギャモン君。
あっ？！　ああ。
Let's go, Gammon.
Huh? 'kay.
Just because Kaito's like that,
まあ　カイトが　ああだからって→
お前まで　つきあって
元気なくすことは…。
you shouldn't be so depressed as w--
カイトを励ます会を開催します！
（２人）あっ。
Let's begin the party to cheer Kaito up!
あっ　いや…　そういう雰囲気じゃ。
That isn't exactly...
思うに　アナも賛成です。
やめたほうが…。
I think... that's a great idea!
We shouldn't...
Let's decide by majority vote!
多数決をとります。
あぁ？
開催した方がいいと思う
√学園の生徒。
All Root Academy students who agree!
（ノノハ・アナ）は～い！　はいはいはい。
お　お　おい。
Me!
Me! Me!
Come on...
Me! Me! Me!
Me! Me! Me! Me!
Me! Me! Me! Me! Me!
Me! Me! Me! Me! Me! Me!
Me! Me! Me! Me! Me! Me! Me!
Me! Me! Me! Me! Me! Me! Me! Me!
うっ。　どんどん難しくなる。
It's getting harder...
皮肉だな。　数字が　こんなにも
僕を苦しめるなんて。
It's ironic that numbers can torture me like this.
数式が得意だからこそ
分かるんだ。
I'm good with numbers,
最後の問題が　制限以内に
解けるかどうかは　五分と五分。
so I know that the chances of solving the last problem within the given time is 50-50.
（フンガ）もう　お逃げになった方が
よろしいのでは？
How about running away?
Look! Death is this close already.
ほら！
死が　もう　すぐそこまで…。
Then if you'll allow me, I will take my leave.
（フンガ）では　そろそろ私は
退散させていただきます。
I am not so kind as to tag along with fool's play for so long.
これ以上　愚か者につきあうほど
お人よしではありませんので。
（キュービック）このまま　何もかも捨てて
逃げ出すか？
Should I give it all up and run away?
それとも　諦めないで
戦うか？
Or fight without giving up?
どうする…　どうする。
What should I do? What should I do?
そんなの　決まってる！
カイトなら…。
That should be obvious! Kaito would...
カイトなら迷ったりしない！　イヒッ！
Kaito would never hesitate!
心の声
やんないで　後悔するくらいなら
やって　後悔する！
It's better to regret doing something than not doing something!
ううん。　負けることなんて
はなっから　考えちゃいない！
Yeah, I mustn't even consider losing!
勝ち気で　まっすぐで意地っ張りで
そのくせ　ちょっぴり　てれ屋で→
Go all out relentlessly!
That and being just a bit self-conscious...
そんなカイトが　僕は大好きなんだ！
That's why I love Kaito so much!
僕は　カイトみたいに
なりたいんだ～！
I want to be like him!
（扉の開く音）
（フンガ）お見事でした。
Well done.
僕は勝った！　ルークに。
はい。
I won! I defeated Rook!
You did.
（フンガ）まだ幼き頃の　あのお方に。
When he was a child, that is.
ルーク様が　このパズルを
お作りになったのは→
Sir Rook made this puzzle right on one of his birthdays.
ちょうど　ご自身の
お誕生日でした。　５歳の。
The fifth.
５歳？！
そんな年で　このパズルを？！
The fifth?! He made a puzzle like this at that age?!
Do you not think that a person of such amazing talent is more worthy to be at Daimon Kaito's side?
そういう　たぐいまれなる能力を
持ったお方こそが→
大門カイトと共に居るに
ふさわしいと思いませんか？
ねえ　天才君。
Right, little genius?
ユニオンジャックのアップルジュースは酸っぱいね。
Union Jack apple juice is so sour!
Well, as a failure of a child of the Phi Brain, what could I do?
さて　ファイ・ブレインの子供として
産み落とされなかった僕には→
一体　何ができるかな？
というわけで　パズルとノズルは　きっと
親戚に違いないって思うよね。
So I think that puzzles and nozzles are certainly closely related!
さすがのアナも　それは
思わないっちゅう　パズルイ陣営。
Not even I think so, and I'm a puzzler.
（２人）どうも失礼しました。
（パフパフラッパの音）
（鐘の音）
Well, excuse us!
There is the Genius Terrace...
天才テラスと掛けまして。
掛けまして…。
The Genius Terrace...
パズル部の部員と解く。
そのココロは？
And a member of the Puzzle Club.
What's the common thing?
思うに　どちらも白夜の砂漠に咲く
ポロロゲ草に似た音色が特徴でしょう。
I think... they both have the tone of cactus flowers blooming in the desert night!
うまい！　…んだか　なんだか
分かんないけど。
Great! Though I don't get it.
とにかく　アナらしい！
（パフパフラッパの音）
But it's so much like you!
あっ！　カイト！
Kaito!
今　カイトを励ます会　やってんの。
キューちゃんも出演して！
We're having a party to cheer Kaito up!
You should do something too, Cubie!
えっ？！
カイトの友達でしょう。　お願い！
You're his friend, right? Please!
ごめん。　僕　ちょっと　ノド
渇いちゃった。　ジュース買ってくるよ。
Sorry, I'm a bit thirsty. I'll go get something to drink.
（ギャモン）おい　逃げんな！
みんなの分も買ってくるから。
Hey, don't run away!
I'll buy some for you too.
どうしたんだろ？
What's wrong with him?
まっ　いきなり　出し物やれって
言われたって　できる訳ねえわな。
Well, no surprise he couldn't improvise when you asked him so suddenly.
じゃあ　ギャモン君やって！
はぁ？！
Then you do something, Gammon!
さっきからアナと私ばっかりじゃん。
あんたも　何か　やりなさいよ！
It's been just Ana and me the whole time.
You do something too!
Okay, then...
（ギャモン）じゃ　じゃあ…
幼なじみの親友と掛けまして…。
There's an old childhood friend...
いきなり
なんちゅうもんと掛けまんねん。
No, there isn't!
How can you do that?!
お前　なんちゅう技　掛けんだ…。
tsukue no ue de umareta sekai
This world born on my table.
ichiban saki ni kimi ni misetakatta
I wanted you to see it first.
karappo no heya sotto nukedashite hashiri hajimeteta
I sneaked out of the empty room and started to run.
iki hazamasete oka wo noboru to
As I got to the top of the hill, out of breath,
kimi ga saki ni tsuite matteita ne
you were already there waiting for me.
takusan no hajimete kimi to mitsuketa takaramono datta
It was the first of many treasures we would find together.
kanashisa de afureta toki wa
When sorrow was overflowing in me,
nanimo iwazu ni tada soba ni ite kureta ne
you just silently stayed by my side.
ima de mo wasurenai yo
I still haven't forgotten that.
mata aou ne yakusoku wo shiyou
Let's promise we'll meet again.
kie wa shinai ano hi no sayonara
The goodbye of that day we'll never forget.
boku no subete kimi ga kureta michi
All I have I got from you,
zutto kokoro no naka hikaru yo
and it will all shine in my heart forever.